Inventory of the Arsenii Ivanovich Formakov papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Arsenii Ivanovich Formakov papers
1910's-1983
2002C37
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet)
Memoirs, other writings, correspondence, and photographs, relating to conditions in forced labor camps in the Soviet Union.
Formakov, Arsenii Ivanovich, 1922-1983.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2002.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
1900 March 15 Born, Libava, Latvia
1920s Studied at Institute of Engineering in Petrograd, Russia
1920s Teacher in Daugavpils, Latvia
1920s Editor of Dvinskii Golos (Voice of Dvinsk)
1925 Author, Vechera Proshlogo, collected poems
1926 Author, V Puti, collected poems, Dvinsk
1930 Author, Nasha Iunost', novel
1932 June 12 Married Anna Ivanovna Zakaznova
1934 Author, Vstrecha, collected poems, Daugavpils
1938 Author, Faina, novel
1940 - 1947 December Exiled to Siberia
1949 September - 1955 August Exiled to Siberia for the second time
1955 August Returned to Riga after amnesty
1960s through 1980s Worked for local Latvian radio music programs
1960s through 1980s Translator of Latvian poetry
1983 March 7 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Arsenii Ivanovich Formakov, Latvia-based Russian poet, teacher, journalist, and writer who was twice exiled to Siberia, consist of correspondence, memoirs, other writings, and photographs, relating to conditions in forced labor camps in the Soviet Union. The Correspondence contains letters from Formakov to his wife and children and letters to Formakov, from other poets and publishers. Included are several copies of letters from Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn, relating to his gulag book and labor camps. The Writings includes memoirs, stories, and poems. The Printed Matter includes poems, songs lyrics, and music scores by other poets and songwriters. The Miscellany includes Formakov's watercolor drawings, portaits, drawings from labor camps, clippings, and other documents. The Photographs consists of four photo albums with prints depicting family life scenes and other topics.
Forced labor--Soviet Union.; Latvia.
- Correspondence, 1941-1968. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains Arsenii Formakov's letters to and from his children, wife, and others, during his stay in Soviet forced labor camps. Included are copies of letters from Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn.
  - Arsenii Formakov to his children, Evgeniia and Dmitrii, 1944-1955 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Arsenii Formakov to his wife Anna, 1941-1947 (Box 1)
    - 1941-1947 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - 1945 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - 1946 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - 1947 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - 1948-1962 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Arsenii Formakov to his wife and children, undated (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - From his wife, 1953-1955 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - From his children, 1950-1951 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - From friends and other poets, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - From Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - From publishers, 1956-1968 (Box-folder 1: 12)
- Writings, 1926-1957 and undated. (Box 1-2)
  Includes Arsenii Formakov's memoirs, poems, stories, and musical stories.
  - Memoirs, undated (Box-folder 1: 13-14)
  - Musical story, undated (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Musical stories, undated (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Musical stories, after 1955 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Stories, undated (Box-folder 2: 3-4)
  - Stories, after 1955 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Poems and notes, 1926-1957 (Box-folder 2: 6)
- Printed Matter, 1970s and undated. (Box-folder 2: 7-10)
  Includes poems and song lyrics by other poets and songwriters.
  - Notebook with music scores and lyrics by Alexander Vertinsky and other song writers. (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Poems (Box-folder 2: 8-9)
    - Severyanin, Igor, 1975 (Box-folder 2: 8)
    - Other poets and songwriters, 1972 and undated (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Song lyrics by Alexander Vertinsky, undated (Box-folder 2: 10)
- Miscellany, undated (Box-folder 2: 11-13)
  - Book cover (handmade of wood) (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Drawings, clippings, other documents. Includes signed photograph of Yuri Gagarin (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Watercolor drawings by Arsenii Formakov (Box-folder 2: 13)
- Photographs, 1920s through 1930s, and undated. (Box 3)
  Includes four photo albums with prints depicticting family members and scenes of daily life, places, and other topics